<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-wilde-service-link-rel-00">
   <front>
      <title abbrev="Web Services Link Relation Types">Link Relation Types for Web Services</title>
      <author initials="E." surname="Wilde" fullname="Erik Wilde">
         <organization>UC Berkeley</organization>
         <address>
            <email>dret@berkeley.edu</email>
            <uri>http://dret.net/netdret/</uri>
         </address>
      </author>
      <date day="21" month="April" year="2015"/>
      <abstract>
         <t>Many resources provided on the Web are part of a sets of resources that are provided in a context that is defined and managed by one particular service provider. Often, these sets of resources are referred to as "Web Services" or "Web APIs". This specification defines two link relations that allows to represent relationships from those resources to ones that provide documentation or descriptions of the Web services. The difference between these concepts is that documentation is primarily intended for human consumers, whereas descriptions are primarily intended for automated consumers.</t>
      </abstract>
   </front>
   <middle>
      <section title="Introduction" anchor="introduction">
         <t>One of the defiing aspects of the Web is that it is possible to interact with Web resources without any specific prior knowledge of the specific of the resource. By using URIs, HTTP, and media types, the Web's uniform interface allows interactions with resources without the sometimes considerably more complex binding procedures of other approaches.</t>
         <t>However, many resources on the Web still are provided as part of some set of resources that often are referred to as a "Web Service" or a "Web API". In many cases, these services or APIs are defined and managed as a whole, and it may be desirable for clients to be able to discover this information.</t>
         <t>Service definition can be separated into two broad categories: One category is entirely targeted for human users and often uses generic formats or human readable documents, such as HTML or PDF. The other category is structured information that followed some more formalized description model, and is intended for consumption my machines, for example for tools and libraries.</t>
         <t>In the context of this specification, the human-oriented variant is referred to as "documentation", and the machine-oriented variant is referred to as "description".</t>
         <t>These two categories are not always mutually exclusive, as there are numerous formats that have been proposed that are intended for both human consumption, and for interpretation by machine clients.</t>
         <t>This specification makes no assumptions about the specific formats used for either of those two categories. It simply assumes that the publisher of a resource may want to make the documentation and/or the description discoverable, and defines two link relations that serve that purpose.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Terminology" anchor="terminology">
         <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Web Services" anchor="web-services">
         <t>...</t>
         <section title="Documenting Web Services" anchor="doc-web-services">
            <t>...</t>
         </section>
         <section title="Describing Web Services" anchor="desc-web-services">
            <t>...</t>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Link Relations for Web Services" anchor="link-relations">
         <t>...</t>
         <section title="The service-doc Link Relation Type" anchor="link-rel-service-doc">
            <t>...</t>
         </section>
         <section title="The service-desc Link Relation Type" anchor="link-rel-service-desc">
            <t>...</t>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="security-considerations">
         <t>The link relation types below have been registered by IANA per Section 6.2.1 of RFC 5988 <xref target="RFC5988"/>:</t>
         <section title="Link Relation Type: link-doc">
            <t>
               <list>
                  <t>Relation Name: service-doc</t>
                  <t>Description: Linking to service documentation that is primarily intended for human consumption.</t>
                  <t>Reference: [[ This document ]]</t>
               </list>
            </t>
         </section>
         <section title="Link Relation Type: link-desc">
            <t>
               <list>
                  <t>Relation Name: service-desc</t>
                  <t>Description: Linking to service description that is primarily intended for consumption by machines.</t>
                  <t>Reference: [[ This document ]]</t>
               </list>
            </t>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Security Considerations">
         <t>...</t>
      </section>
<!--
      <section title="Change Log" anchor="change-log">
         <t>Note to RFC Editor: Please remove this section before publication.</t>
         <section title="From -00 to -01">
            <t>
               <list style="symbols">
                  <t>...</t>
               </list>
            </t>
         </section>
      </section>
-->
   </middle>
   <back>
      <references title="Normative References">
         <reference anchor="RFC2119">
            <front>
               <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
               <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner"/>
               <date month="March" year="1997"/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
         </reference>
         <reference anchor="RFC5988">
            <front>
               <title>Web Linking</title>
               <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham"/>
               <date month="October" year="2010"/>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5988"/>
         </reference>
      </references>
<!--
      <references title="Informative References">
      </references>
-->
<!--
      <section title="Acknowledgements">
         <t>Thanks for comments and suggestions provided by Mark Nottingham.</t>
      </section>
 -->
   </back>
</rfc>
