<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<!-- $Id: draft-wilde-sms-uri-18.xml 716 2009-08-06 23:13:25Z dret $ -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200811" docName="draft-wilde-sms-uri-18">
	<front>
		<title abbrev='"sms" URI Scheme'>URI Scheme for GSM Short Message Service</title>
		<author initials="E." surname="Wilde" fullname="Erik Wilde">
			<organization>UC Berkeley</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<city>Berkeley, CA 94720-4600</city>
					<country>U.S.A.</country>
				</postal>
				<phone>+1-510-6432253</phone>
				<email>dret@berkeley.edu</email>
				<uri>http://dret.net/netdret/</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="A." surname="Vaha-Sipila" fullname="Antti Vaha-Sipila">
			<organization>Nokia</organization>
			<address>
				<email>antti.vaha-sipila@nokia.com</email>
				<uri>http://www.iki.fi/avs/</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date day="6" month="Aug" year="2009"/>
		<abstract>
			<t>This memo specifies the Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) scheme "sms" for specifying one or more recipients for an SMS message. SMS messages are two-way paging messages that can be sent from and received by a mobile phone or a suitably equipped networked device.</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
			<t>The capitalized key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
			<section title="What is GSM?">
				<t>GSM (Global System for Mobile Communications) is a digital mobile phone standard which is used extensively in many parts of the world. First named after its frequency band around 900 MHz, GSM-900 has provided the basis for several other networks utilizing GSM technology, in particular GSM networks operating in the frequency bands around 1800 MHz and 1900 MHz. When referring to "GSM" in this document, we mean any of these GSM-based networks that operate a short message service.</t>
			</section>
			<section title="What is SMS?" anchor="sms-descr">
				<t>The Short Message Service (SMS) <xref target="SMS"/> is an integral part of the GSM network technology. It has been very successful and currently is a major source of revenue for many GSM operators. SMS as a service is so successful that other Global Switched Telephone Network (GSTN) technologies have adapted it as well, in particular the Integrated Services Digital Network (ISDN). Because of this development, this memo uses the term "SMS client" to refer to user agents who are able to send and/or receive SMS messages.</t>
				<section title="SMS content">
					<t>GSM SMS messages are alphanumeric paging messages that can be sent to and from SMS clients. SMS messages have a maximum length of 160 characters (7-bit characters from the GSM character set <xref target="SMS-CHAR"/>), or 140 octets. Other character sets (such as UCS-2 16-bit characters, resulting in 70 character messages) MAY also be supported <xref target="SMS-CHAR"/>, but are defined as being optional by the SMS specification. Consequently, applications handling SMS messages as part of a chain of character processing applications MUST make sure that character sets are correctly mapped to and from the character set used for SMS messages.</t>
					<t>While the 160 character variety for SMS messages is by far the most widely used one, there are numerous other content types for SMS messages, such as small bitmaps ("operator logos") and simple formats for musical notes ("ring tones"). However, these formats are proprietary and are not considered in this memo.</t>
					<t>SMS messages are limited in length (140 octets), and the first versions of the SMS specification did not specify any standardized methods for concatenating SMS messages. As a consequence, several proprietary methods were invented, but the current SMS specification does specify message concatenation. In order to deal with this situation, SMS clients composing messages SHOULD use the standard concatenation method based on the header in the TP-User Data field as specified in the SMS specification <xref target="SMS"/>. When sending a message to an SMS recipient whose support for concatenated messages is unknown, the SMS client MAY opt to use the backwards-compatible (text-based) concatenation method defined in the SMS specification <xref target="SMS"/>. Proprietary concatenation methods SHOULD NOT be used except in closed systems, where the capabilities of the recipient(s) are always known.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="SMS infrastructure">
					<t>SMS messages can be transmitted over an SMS client's network interface using the signaling channels of the underlying GSTN infrastructure, so there is no delay for call setup. Alternatively, SMS messages may be submitted through other front-ends (for example Web-based services), which makes it possible for SMS clients to run on computers which are not directly connected to a GSTN network supporting SMS.</t>
					<t>SMS messages sent with the GSTN SMS service MUST be sent as class 1 SMS messages, if the client is able to specify the message class.</t>
					<section title="SMS Centers" anchor="smscenter">
						<t>For delivery within GSTN networks, SMS messages are stored by an entity called SMS Center (SMSC), and sent to the recipient when the subscriber connects to the network. The number of a cooperative SMSC must be known to the SMS sender (i.e., the entity submitting the SMS message to a GSTN infrastructure) when sending the message (usually, the SMSC's number is configured in the SMS client and specific for the network operator to which the sender has subscribed). In most situations, the SMSC number is part of the sending SMS client's configuration. However, in some special cases (such as when the SMS recipient only accepts messages from a certain SMSC), it may be necessary to send the SMS message over a specific SMSC. The scheme specified in this memo does not support the specification of SMSC numbers, so in case of scenarios where messages have to be sent through a certain SMSC, there must be some other context establishing this requirement, or message delivery may fail.</t>
					</section>
				</section>
				<section title="Uniform Resource Identifiers">
					<t>One of the core specifications for identifying resources on the Internet is RFC 3986 <xref target="RFC3986"/>, specifying the syntax and semantics of a Uniform Resource Identifier (URI). The most important notion of URIs are "schemes", which define a framework within which resources can be uniquely identified and addressed. URIs enable users to access resources, and are used for very diverse schemes such as access protocols (HTTP, FTP), broadcast media (TV channels <xref target="RFC2838"/>), messaging (email <xref target="RFC2368"/>), and even telephone numbers (voice <xref target="RFC3966"/>).</t>
					<t>URIs often are mentioned together with Uniform Resource Names (URNs) and/or Uniform Resource Locators (URLs), and it often is unclear how to separate these concepts. For the purpose of this memo, only the term URI will be used, referring to the most fundamental concept. The World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) has issued a note <xref target="uri-clarification"/> discussing the topic of URIs, URNs, and URLs in detail.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="SMS Messages and the Internet">
					<t>One of the important reasons for the universal access of the Web is the ability to access all information through a unique interface. This kind of integration makes it easy to provide information as well as to consume it. One aspect of this integration is the support of user agents (in the case of the Web, commonly referred to as browsers) for multiple content formats (such as HTML, GIF, JPEG) and access schemes (such as HTTP, HTTPS, FTP).</t>
					<t>The "mailto" scheme has proven to be very useful and popular, because most user agents support it by providing an email composition facility when the user selects (e.g., clicks on) the URI. Similarly, the "sms" scheme can be supported by user agents by providing an SMS message composition facility when the user selects the URI. In cases where the user agent does not provide a built-in SMS message composition facility, the scheme could still be supported by opening a Web page which provides such a service. The specific Web page to be used could be configured by the user, so that each user could use the SMS message composition service of his choice.</t>
					<t>The goal of this memo is to specify the "sms" URI scheme, so that user agents (such as Web browsers and email clients) can start to support it. The "sms" URI scheme identifies SMS message endpoints as resources. When "sms" URIs are dereferenced, implementations MAY create a message and present it to be edited before being sent, or they MAY invoke additional services to provide the functionality necessary for composing a message and sending it to the SMS message endpoint. In either case, simply activating a link with an "sms" URI SHOULD NOT cause a message to be sent without prior user confirmation.</t>
					<section title="SMS Messages and the Web">
						<t>SMS messages can provide an alternative to "mailto" URIs <xref target="RFC2368"/>, or "tel" or "fax" URIs <xref target="RFC3966"/>. When a "sms" URI is activated, the user agent MAY start a program for sending an SMS message, just as "mailto" may open a mail client. Unfortunately, most browsers do not support the external handling of internally unsupported URI schemes in the same generalized way as most of them support external handling of content for media types which they do not support internally. Ideally, user agents should implement generic URI parsers and provide a way to associate unsupported schemes with external applications (or Web-based services).</t>
						<t>The recipient of an SMS message need not be a mobile phone. It can be a server that can process SMS messages, either by gatewaying them to another messaging system (such as regular electronic mail), or by parsing them for supplementary services.</t>
						<t>SMS messages can be used to transport almost any kind of data (even though there is a very tight size limit), but the only standardized data formats are character-based messages in different character encodings. SMS messages have a maximum length of 160 characters (when using 7-bit characters from the SMS character set), or 140 octets. However, SMS messages can be concatenated to form longer messages. It is up to the user agent to decide whether to limit the length of the message, and how to indicate this limit in its user interface, if necessary. There is one exception to this, see <xref target="htmlforms"/>.</t>
					</section>
					<section title="SMS Messages and Forms">
						<t>The Hypertext Markup Language (HTML) <xref target="HTML401"/> provides a way to collect information from a user and pass it to a server for processing. This functionality is known as "HTML forms". A filled-in form is usually sent to the destination using the Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) or email. However, SMS messages can also be used as the transport mechanism for these forms. Depending on the network configuration, the sender's telephone number may be included in the SMS message, thus providing a weak form of authentication.</t>
					</section>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title='The "sms" URI Scheme' anchor="uri-syntax">
			<t>Syntax definitions are given using the Augmented BNF (ABNF) for syntax specifications <xref target="RFC5234"/>.</t>
			<section title="Applicability">
				<t>This URI scheme provides information that can be used for sending an SMS message to certain recipient(s). The functionality is comparable to that of the "mailto" URI, which (as per RFC 2368 <xref target="RFC2368"/>) can also be used with a comma-separated list of email addresses.</t>
				<t>The notation for phone numbers is taken from <xref target="RFC3966"/> and its Erratum 203. <xref target="telephone-subscriber-syntax"/> provides a corrected syntax of the telephone number. Refer to this document for information on why this particular format was chosen.</t>
				<t>How the SMS message is sent to the SMSC or other intermediaries is outside the scope of this specification. SMS messages can be sent over the GSM air interface, by using a modem and a suitable protocol, or by accessing services over other protocols, such as a Web-based service for sending SMS messages. Also, SMS message service options like deferred delivery and delivery notification requests are not within the scope of this document. Such services MAY be requested from the network by the user agent if necessary.</t>
				<t>SMS messages sent as a result of this URI MUST be sent as class 1 SMS messages, if the user agent is able to specify the message class.</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Formal Definition" anchor="syntaxdef">
				<t>The URI scheme's keywords specified in the following syntax description are case-insensitive. The syntax of an "sms" URI is formally described as follows, where the URI base syntax is taken from RFC 3986 <xref target="RFC3986"/>:</t>
				<t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
sms-uri         =  scheme ":" sms-hier-part [ "?" sms-fields ]
scheme          =  "sms"
sms-hier-part   =  sms-recipient *( "," sms-recipient )
sms-recipient   =  telephone-subscriber ; defined in RFC 3966
sms-fields      =  sms-field *( "&amp;" sms-field )
sms-field       =  sms-field-name "=" escaped-value  ; "body" MUST only appear once
sms-field-name  =  "body" / sms-field-ext
sms-field-ext   =  *( unreserved ) 
escaped-value   =  *( unreserved / pct-encoded ) ; defined in RFC 3986</artwork>
					</figure>
				</t>
				<t>Some illustrative examples using this syntax are given in <xref target="uri-examples"/>.</t>
				<t>The syntax definition for &lt;telephone-subscriber> is taken from RFC 3966 <xref target="RFC3966"/> (Section 5.1). Please consider Erratum 203 in that specification. For the reader's convenience, <xref target="telephone-subscriber-syntax"/> contains a fixed syntax of the telephone number URI scheme including Erratum 203, but RFC 3966 (plus all applicable errata) is the normative reference. The description of phone numbers in RFC 3966 states (quoted from RFC 3966, Section 5.1): "The 'telephone-subscriber' part of the URI indicates the number.  The phone number can be represented in either global (E.164) or local notation.  All phone numbers MUST use the global form unless they cannot be represented as such.  Numbers from private numbering plans, emergency ('911', '112'), and some directory-assistance numbers (e.g., '411') and other 'service codes' (numbers of the form N11 in the United States) cannot be represented in global (E.164) form and need to be represented as a local number with a context.  Local numbers MUST be tagged with a 'phone-context'."</t>
				<t>SMS URIs may use additional fields, as indicated by the &lt;sms-fields> token. The only field defined here is the "body" &lt;sms-field>. Extensions to this specification MAY add additional fields. Extensions MUST NOT change the semantics of the specifications they are extending. Unknown fields encountered in SMS URIs MUST be ignored by implementations.</t>
				<t>The "body" &lt;sms-field> is used to define the body of the SMS message to be composed. It consists of percent-encoded UTF-8 characters. Implementations MUST make sure that the "body" &lt;sms-field> characters are converted to a suitable character encoding before sending, the most popular being the 7-bit SMS character encoding, another variant (though not as universally supported as 7-bit SMS) is the UCS-2 character encoding  (both specified in <xref target="SMS-CHAR"/>). Implementations MAY choose to discard (or convert) characters in the &lt;sms-body> that are not supported by the SMS character set they are using to send the SMS message. If they do discard or convert characters, they MUST notify the user.</t>
				
				<t>The syntax definition for &lt;escaped-value> refers to the text of an SMS where all &lt;reserved> (as per RFC 3986 <xref target="RFC3986"/>) characters in the SMS text are percent-encoded, please refer to RFC 3986 <xref target="RFC3986"/> for the definition &lt;unreserved> and &lt;pct-encoded>, and the details about percent-encoding.</t>
				<t>User agents SHOULD support multiple recipients, and SHOULD make it clear to users what the entire list of recipients is, before committing the user to sending all the messages.</t>
			</section>
			<section title='Processing an "sms" URI' anchor="processing">
				<t>The following list describes the steps for processing an "sms" URI:</t>
				<t>
					<list style="numbers">
						<t>The phone number of the first &lt;sms-recipient> is extracted. It is the phone number of the final recipient and it MUST be written in international form with country code, unless the number only works from inside a certain geographical area or a network. Note that some numbers may work from several networks but not from the whole world - these SHOULD be written in international form. According to RFC 3966 <xref target="RFC3966"/>, all international numbers MUST begin with a "+" character. Hyphens, dots, and parentheses (referred to as "visual separators" in RFC 3966) are used only to improve readability and MUST NOT convey any other meaning.</t>
						<t>The "body" &lt;sms-field> is extracted, if present.</t>
						<t>The user agent SHOULD provide some means for message composition, either by implementing this itself, or by accessing a service providing it. Message composition SHOULD start with the body extracted from the "body" &lt;sms-field>, if present.</t>
						<t>After message composition, a user agent SHOULD try to send the message first using the default delivery method employed by that user agent. If that fails, the user agent MAY try another delivery method.</t>
						<t>If the URI consists of a comma-separated list of recipients (i.e., contains multiple &lt;sms-recipient> parts), all of them are processed in this manner. Exactly the same message SHOULD be sent to all of the listed recipients, which means that the message resulting from the message composition step for the first recipient is used unaltered for all other recipients as well.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Examples of Use" anchor="uri-examples">
				<t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>sms:+17775555555</artwork>
					</figure>
				</t>
				<t>This indicates an SMS message capable recipient at the given telephone number. The message is sent using the user agent's default SMS delivery method.</t>
				<t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>sms:+17775555555,+15557777777</artwork>
					</figure>
				</t>
				<t>This indicates SMS message capable recipients at the given telephone numbers. The identical message should be sent to both recipients using the user agent's default SMS delivery method.</t>
				<t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>sms:+17775555555?body=hello%20there</artwork>
					</figure>
				</t>
				<t>In this case, a message (initially being set to "hello there", which may be modified by the user before sending) will be sent via SMS using the user agent's default SMS delivery method.</t>
			</section>
			<section title='Using "sms" URIs in HTML Forms' anchor="htmlforms">
				<t>When using a "sms" type URI as an action URI for HTML form submission <xref target="HTML401"/>, the form contents MUST be packaged in the SMS message just as they are packaged when using a "mailto" URI <xref target="RFC2368"/>, using the "application/x-www-form-urlencoded" media type (as defined by HTML <xref target="HTML401"/>), effectively packaging all form data into URI compliant syntax <xref target="RFC3986"/>. The SMS message MUST NOT contain any HTTP headers, only the form data. The media type is implicit. It MUST NOT be transferred in the SMS message. Since the SMS message contains the form field values, the body &lt;sms-field> of an "sms" type URI used for an HTML form will be ignored.</t>
				<t>The character encoding used for form submissions MUST be UTF-8 <xref target="RFC3629"/>. It should be noted, however, that user agents MUST percent-encode form submissions before sending them (this encoding is specified by the URI syntax <xref target="RFC3986"/>).</t>
				<t>The user agent SHOULD inform the user about the possible security hazards involved when submitting the form (it is probably being sent as plain text over an air interface).</t>
				<t>If the form submission is longer than the maximum SMS message size, the user agent MAY either concatenate SMS messages, if it is able to do so, or it MAY refuse to send the message. The user agent MUST NOT send out partial form submissions.</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="URI Scheme Registration" anchor="registration">
			<t>This memo requests the registration of the Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) scheme "sms" for specifying one or more recipients for an SMS message. The registration request complies with RFC 4395 <xref target="RFC4395"/>.</t>
			<section title="URI Scheme Name">
				<t>sms</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Status">
				<t>Provisional</t>
			</section>
			<section title="URI Scheme Syntax">
				<t>See <xref target="uri-syntax"/>.</t>
			</section>
			<section title="URI Scheme Semantics">
				<t>The "sms" defines a way how a message may be composed which is then transmitted using the SMS message transmission method. This scheme can thus be compared to be "mailto" URI scheme <xref target="RFC2368"/>. See <xref target="processing"/> for the details of operation.</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Encoding Considerations">
				<t>The optional body field of "sms" URIs may contain a message text, but this text uses percent-encoded UTF-8 characters and thus can always be represented using URI characters. See <xref target="uri-syntax"/> for the details of encoding.</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Applications/Protocols that use this URI Scheme Name">
				<t>The "sms" URI scheme is intended to be used in a similar way as the "mailto" URI scheme <xref target="RFC2368"/>. By using "sms" URIs, authors can embed information into documents which can be used as a starting point for initiating message composition. Whether the client is sending the message itself (for example over a GSM air interface) or redirecting the user to a third party for message composition (such as a Web service for sending SMS messages) is outside of the scope of the URI scheme definition.</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Interoperability Considerations">
				<t>No interoperability issues have been identified.</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Security Considerations">
				<t>See <xref target="security"/>.</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Contact">
				<figure>
					<artwork>
Erik Wilde
School of Information
UC Berkeley
Berkeley, CA 94720-4600
U.S.A.
tel:+1-510-6432252
mailto:dret@berkeley.edu
						</artwork>
				</figure>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
			<t>SMS messages are transported without any provisions for privacy or integrity, so SMS users should be aware of these inherent security problems of SMS messages. Unlike electronic mail, where additional mechanisms exist to layer security features on top of the basic infrastructure, there currently is no such framework for SMS messages.</t>
			<t>SMS messages very often are delivered almost instantaneously (if the receiving SMS client is online), but there is no guarantee for when SMS messages will be delivered. In particular, SMS messages between different network operators sometimes take a long time to be delivered (hours or even days) or are not delivered at all, so applications SHOULD NOT make any assumptions about the reliability and performance of SMS message transmission.</t>
			<t>In most networks, sending SMS messages is not a free service. Therefore, SMS clients MUST make sure that any action that incurs costs is acknowledged by the end user, unless explicitly instructed otherwise by the end user. If an SMS client has different ways of submitting an SMS message (such as a Web service and a phone line), then the end user MUST have a way to control which way is chosen.</t>
			<t>SMS clients often are limited devices (typically mobile phones), and the sending SMS client SHOULD NOT make any assumptions about the receiving SMS client supporting any non-standard services, such as proprietary message concatenation or proprietary content types. However, if the sending SMS client has prior knowledge about the receiving SMS client, then he MAY use this knowledge to compose non-standard SMS messages.</t>
			<t>There are certain special SMS messages defined in the SMS specification <xref target="SMS"/> that can be used, for example, to turn on indicators on the phone display, or to send data to certain communication ports (comparable to UDP ports) on the device. Certain proprietary systems (for example, the Wireless Application Protocol <xref target="WAP"/>) define configuration messages that may be used to reconfigure the devices remotely. Any SMS client SHOULD make sure that malicious use of such messages is not possible, for example by filtering out certain SMS User Data headers. Gateways that accept SMS messages e.g. in e-mail messages or Web forms and pass them on to an SMSC, SHOULD implement this kind of "firewalling" approach as well.</t>
			<t>Because the narrow bandwidth of the SMS communications channel, there should also be checks in place for excessively long concatenated messages. As an example, it may take two minutes to transfer thirty concatenated text messages.</t>
			<t>Unchecked input from a user MUST NOT be used to populate any other fields in a SMS message other than the User Data field (not including the User Data Header field). All other parts, including the User Data Header, of the short message should only be generated by trusted means.</t>
			<t>By including "sms" URIs in unsolicited messages (a.k.a. "spam") or other types of advertising, the originator of the "sms" URIs may attempt to reveal an individual's phone number and/or to link the identity (i.e., e-mail address) used for messaging with the identity (i.e., phone number) used for the mobile phone. This attempt to collect information may be a privacy issue, and user agents may make users aware of that risk before composing or sending SMS messages. Users agents which do not provide any feedback about this privacy issue make users more vulnerable to this kind of attack.</t>
			<t>A user agent SHOULD NOT send out SMS messages without the knowledge of the user, because of associated risks, which include sending masses of SMS messages to a subscriber without his consent, and the costs involved in sending an SMS message.</t>
			<t>As suggested functionality, the user agent MAY offer a possibility for the user to filter out those phone numbers that are expressed in local format, as most premium-rate numbers are expressed in local format, and because determining the correct local context (and hence the validity of the number to this specific user) may be very difficult.</t>
			<t>When using "sms" URIs as targets of forms (as described in <xref target="htmlforms"/>), the user agent SHOULD inform the user about the possible security hazards involved when submitting the form (it is probably being sent as plain text over an air interface).</t>
		</section>
		<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
			<t>Upon publication of this memo as an RFC, IANA has registered the "sms" URI scheme, using the template in <xref target="registration"/>, in accordance with RFC 4395 <xref target="RFC4395"/>.</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Change Log">
			<t>This section will not be part of the final RFC text, it serves as a container to collect the history of the individual draft versions. To the editor: Please remove this section before publication as RFC.</t>
			<section title="From -17 to -18">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Added normative reference to <xref target="HTML401"/> for the "application/x-www-form-urlencoded" media type.</t>
						<t>Changed &lt;sms-body> to become &lt;sms-field> (with "body" as the only predefined field name) and &lt;escaped-sms> to become &lt;escaped-value>, to allow extensions and defined extension model to be mustIgnore.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -16 to -17">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Changed phone numbers in <xref target="uri-examples"/> to be clearly identifiable example phone numbers.</t>
						<t>Changed syntax of &lt;sms-body> to use &lt;escaped-sms> (defined internally) instead of &lt;query> (which had been reused from RFC 3986).</t>
						<t>Removed RFC 2822 from the references (unused).</t>
						<t>Moved <xref target="uri-syntax"/> outside of <xref target="intro"/>, becoming a top-level section.</t>
						<t>Renamed &lt;hier-part> to &lt;sms-hier-part> to avoid confusion with RFC 3986 tokens.</t>
						<t>Removed unused tokens from <xref target="telephone-subscriber-syntax"/>.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -15 to -16">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Changed phone numbers to be defined by the &lt;telephone-subscriber> part of RFC 3966 <xref target="RFC3966"/> rather than being defined here.</t>
						<t>Removed the intermediate &lt;sms-number> part and defined &lt;sms-recipient> to directly use &lt;telephone-subscriber>.</t>
						<t>Replaced reference to <xref target="RFC5234"/> in <xref target="iana"/> with correct reference to <xref target="RFC4395"/>.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -14 to -15">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>RFC 4234 (ABNF) has been obsoleted by <xref target="RFC5234"/>.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -13 to -14">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Updated abstract of <xref target="registration"/> to the new abstract of the complete document (mentioning of gateway functionality removed).</t>
						<t>Removed the "smsc" qualifier which allowed the specification of an SMSC to be used for SMS message delivery.</t>
						<t>Removed the section about interfacing between a user agent processing an "sms" URI, and a Web-based service for SMS composition and sending.</t>
						<t>Replaced "gstn-phone" with "sms-number" in <xref target="processing"/> (inconsistency from earlier syntax revision).</t>
						<t>Replaced all quotes around ABNF symbols within text with &lt;...> to clearly identify them as ABNF.</t>
						<t>Updated all references to their complete XML version.</t>
						<t>Added <xref target="iana"/>.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -12 to -13">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Updated <xref target="SMS"/> to point to the latest version of the SMS spec (3GPP TS 23.040 V7.0.1).</t>
						<t>Removed support for telematic interworking from the draft. This feature of SMS messaging is hard to understand, poorly supported by clients as well as network operators, and for these reasons would have been likely to see poor adoption in implementations anyway.</t>
						<t>Added some text making it more clear that all recipients SHOULD be sent the exact same message.</t>
						<t>Several small editorial changes.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -11 to -12">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Integrated draft-wilde-sms-service-11 and draft-wilde-sms-uri-registration-00 into this draft. This draft is now self-contained.</t>
						<t>Changed the phone number notation to use the definition from RFC 3966 <xref target="RFC3966"/> rather than RFC 3601 (RFC 3966 is a simpler notation disallowing some of the special characters allowed by RFC 3601).</t>
						<t>Rephrased various parts of <xref target="security"/>.</t>
						<t>Removed Section "Author/Change Controller".</t>
						<t>RFC 2806 (tel URI scheme) has been obsoleted by <xref target="RFC3966"/>.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -10 to -11">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>RFC 2234 (ABNF) has been obsoleted by RFC4234.</t>
						<t>Updated reference information for <xref target="SMS"/> and <xref target="SMS-CHAR"/>.</t>
						<t>Minor textual changes.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -09 to -10">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Added security consideration about filtering local format phone numbers.</t>
						<t>Changed IPR clause from RFC 3667 to RFC 3978 (updated version of RFC 3667).</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -08 to -09">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Fixed syntax error in hier-part and sms-recipient non-terminals, which allowed sms-recipients to be concatenated without comma separation.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -07 to -08">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>URIs are now defined by RFC 3986 <xref target="RFC3986"/>, so the text (including the syntax definitions) and the references have been updated.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -06 to -07">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Changed IPR clause from RFC 2026 to RFC 3667 (updated version of RFC 2026).</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -05 to -06">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Updated reference from draft-allocchio-gstn to RFC 3601.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -04 to -05">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Updated reference to SMS spec to the version referenced in the SMS service draft.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -03 to -04">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Updated reference to draft-allocchio-gstn (to revision -05).</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -02 to -03">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Changed ordering of "change Log" section (descending to ascending).</t>
						<t>Clarified the wording at the beginning of <xref target="syntaxdef"/> about only the keywords of the scheme being case-insensitive.</t>
						<t>Changed "sms-body" to be a URI query string.</t>
						<t>Added some text describing "sms" URIs as addressing resources.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -01 to -02">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Changed the sms-body field to percent-encoded UTF-8 characters.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="From -00 to -01">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Added the "sms-body" field and its processing rules.</t>
						<t>Added section about using "sms" URIs as query strings for SMS Web services.</t>
						<t>Fixed typo in ABNF (said "global-phone" instead of "gstn-phone").</t>
						<t>Added some explanatory text about form submissions using email telematic interworking.</t>
						<t>Added some text about character encoding in form submissions.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Change Log of draft-wilde-sms-service">
				<t>This section contains the change log of draft-wilde-sms-service-11 before it was incorporated into this document at version draft-wilde-sms-uri-12.</t>
				<section title="From -10 to -11">
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>RFC 2234 (ABNF) has been obsoleted by RFC4234.</t>
							<t>Added new security issue in <xref target="security"/>.</t>
							<t>Updated reference information for <xref target="SMS"/> and <xref target="SMS-CHAR"/>.</t>
							<t>Minor textual changes.</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From -09 to -10">
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>Changed IPR clause from RFC 3667 to RFC 3978 (updated version of RFC 3667).</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From -08 to -09">
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>No changes, re-release for alignment with draft-wilde-sms-uri.</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From -07 to -08">
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>No changes, re-release for alignment with draft-wilde-sms-uri.</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From -06 to -07">
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>Changed IPR clause from RFC 2026 to RFC 3667 (updated version of RFC 2026).</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From -05 to -06">
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>Updated reference from draft-allocchio-gstn-05 to RFC 3601.</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From -04 to -05">
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>No changes, re-release for alignment with draft-wilde-sms-uri.</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From -03 to -04">
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>Updated reference to draft-allocchio-gstn (to revision -05).</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From -02 to -03">
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>Changed ordering of "change Log" section (descending to ascending).</t>
							<t>Fixed some spelling errors.</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From -01 to -02">
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>Removed address specification for X.400 SMS from ABNF (surprisingly not part of the SMS spec).</t>
							<t>Added some explanatory text about character set mapping for SMS messages.</t>
							<t>Added text requiring the use of message class 1 for sending SMS messages.</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From -00 to -01">
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>Added a number of new security considerations.</t>
							<t>Added the "PID" qualif-type1 keyword and the section about "SMS Telematic Interworking" (removed in -13, available as Section 1.2.3 in -12).</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="Acknowledgements">
			<t>This document has been prepared using the IETF document DTD described in RFC 2629 <xref target="RFC2629"/>.</t>
			<t>Thanks to (listed alphabetically) Claudio Allocchio, Derek Atkins, Leslie Daigle, Lisa Dusseault, Vijay Gurbani, Alfred Hoenes, Cullen Jennings, Graham Klyne, Larry Masinter, Michael Patton, and Magnus Westerlund for their comments.</t>
		</section>
	</middle>
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			<reference anchor="SMS" target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/archive/23_series/23.040/23040-701.zip">
				<front>
					<title>3GPP TS 23.040 V7.0.1 (2007-03): 3rd Generation Partnership Project; Technical Specification Group Core Network and Terminals; Technical realization of the Short Message Service (SMS) (Release 7)</title>
					<author>
						<organization abbrev="ETSI">European Telecommunications Standards Institute</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="March" year="2007"/>
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="SMS-CHAR" target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/archive/03_series/03.38/0338-720.zip">
				<front>
					<title>TS 100 900 (GSM 03.38 version 7.2.0 Release 1998): Digital Cellular Telecommunications System (Phase 2+); Alphabets and language-specific information</title>
					<author>
						<organization abbrev="ETSI">European Telecommunications Standards Institute</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="July" year="1999"/>
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="HTML401" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/">
				<front>
					<title>HTML 4.01 Specification</title>
					<author initials="D." surname="Raggett" fullname="Dave Raggett">
						<organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="A." surname="Le Hors" fullname="Arnaud Le Hors">
						<organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="I." surname="Jacobs" fullname="Ian Jacobs">
						<organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="December" year="1999"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="W3C" value="REC-html401"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC5234">
				<front>
					<title abbrev="ABNF">Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
					<author fullname="Dave Crocker" initials="D." role="editor" surname="Crocker">
						<organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
						<address>
							<postal>
								<street>675 Spruce Dr.</street>
								<city>Sunnyvale</city>
								<region>CA</region>
								<code>94086</code>
								<country>US</country>
							</postal>
							<phone>+1.408.246.8253</phone>
							<email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
						</address>
					</author>
					<author fullname="Paul Overell" initials="P." surname="Overell">
						<organization>THUS plc.</organization>
						<address>
							<postal>
								<street>1/2 Berkeley Square, </street>
								<street>99 Berkeley Street</street>
								<city>Glasgow</city>
								<code>G3 7HR</code>
								<country>UK</country>
							</postal>
							<email>paul.overell@thus.net</email>
						</address>
					</author>
					<date year="2008" month="January"/>
					<keyword>ABNF</keyword>
					<keyword>Augmented</keyword>
					<keyword>Backus-Naur</keyword>
					<keyword>Form</keyword>
					<keyword>electronic</keyword>
					<keyword>mail</keyword>
					<abstract>
						<t>Internet technical specifications often need to define a formal syntax. Over the years, a modified version of Backus-Naur Form (BNF), called Augmented BNF (ABNF), has been popular among many Internet specifications. The current specification documents ABNF. It balances compactness and simplicity with reasonable representational power. The differences between standard BNF and ABNF involve naming rules, repetition, alternatives, order-independence, and value ranges. This specification also supplies additional rule definitions and encoding for a core lexical analyzer of the type common to several Internet specifications.</t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5234"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC4395">
				<front>
					<title>Guidelines and Registration Procedures for New URI Schemes</title>
					<author initials="T." surname="Hansen" fullname="T. Hansen">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="T." surname="Hardie" fullname="T. Hardie">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="L." surname="Masinter" fullname="L. Masinter">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date year="2006" month="February"/>
					<abstract>
						<t>This document provides guidelines and recommendations for the definition of Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) schemes. It also updates the process and IANA registry for URI schemes. It obsoletes both RFC 2717 and RFC 2718. This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="115"/>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4395"/>
				<format type="TXT" octets="31933" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4395.txt"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC3986">
				<front>
					<title abbrev="URI Generic Syntax">Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
					<author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee" fullname="Tim Berners-Lee">
						<organization abbrev="W3C/MIT">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
						<address>
							<postal>
								<street>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</street>
								<street>77 Massachusetts Avenue</street>
								<city>Cambridge</city>
								<region>MA</region>
								<code>02139</code>
								<country>USA</country>
							</postal>
							<phone>+1-617-253-5702</phone>
							<facsimile>+1-617-258-5999</facsimile>
							<email>timbl@w3.org</email>
							<uri>http://www.w3.org/People/Berners-Lee/</uri>
						</address>
					</author>
					<author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="Roy T. Fielding">
						<organization abbrev="Day Software">Day Software</organization>
						<address>
							<postal>
								<street>5251 California Ave., Suite 110</street>
								<city>Irvine</city>
								<region>CA</region>
								<code>92617</code>
								<country>USA</country>
							</postal>
							<phone>+1-949-679-2960</phone>
							<facsimile>+1-949-679-2972</facsimile>
							<email>fielding@gbiv.com</email>
							<uri>http://roy.gbiv.com/</uri>
						</address>
					</author>
					<author initials="L." surname="Masinter" fullname="Larry Masinter">
						<organization abbrev="Adobe Systems">Adobe Systems Incorporated</organization>
						<address>
							<postal>
								<street>345 Park Ave</street>
								<city>San Jose</city>
								<region>CA</region>
								<code>95110</code>
								<country>USA</country>
							</postal>
							<phone>+1-408-536-3024</phone>
							<email>LMM@acm.org</email>
							<uri>http://larry.masinter.net/</uri>
						</address>
					</author>
					<date year="2005" month="January"/>
					<area>Applications</area>
					<keyword>uniform resource identifier</keyword>
					<keyword>URI</keyword>
					<keyword>URL</keyword>
					<keyword>URN</keyword>
					<keyword>WWW</keyword>
					<keyword>resource</keyword>
					<abstract>
						<t>A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a compact sequence of characters that identifies an abstract or physical resource.  This specification defines the generic URI syntax and a process for resolving URI references that might be in relative form, along with guidelines and security considerations for the use of URIs on the Internet. The URI syntax defines a grammar that is a superset of all valid URIs, allowing an implementation to parse the common components of a URI reference without knowing the scheme-specific requirements of every
			possible identifier.  This specification does not define a generative grammar for URIs; that task is performed by the individual specifications of each URI scheme.</t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="STD" value="66"/>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3986"/>
				<format type="TXT" octets="141811" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3986.txt"/>
				<format type="HTML" octets="213584" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc3986.html"/>
				<format type="XML" octets="163534" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc3986.xml"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC2119">
				<front>
					<title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
					<author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
						<organization>Harvard University</organization>
						<address>
							<postal>
								<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
								<street>Cambridge</street>
								<street>MA 02138</street>
							</postal>
							<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
							<email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
						</address>
					</author>
					<date year="1997" month="March"/>
					<area>General</area>
					<keyword>keyword</keyword>
					<abstract>
						<t>In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification.  These words are often capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:</t>
						<list>
							<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119.</t>
						</list>
						<t>Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement level of the document in which they are used.</t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
				<format type="TXT" octets="4723" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt"/>
				<format type="HTML" octets="17491" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html"/>
				<format type="XML" octets="5777" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC3966">
				<front>
					<title>The tel URI for Telephone Numbers</title>
					<author initials="H." surname="Schulzrinne" fullname="H. Schulzrinne">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date year="2004" month="December"/>
					<abstract>
						<t>This document specifies the URI (Uniform Resource Identifier) scheme "tel". The "tel" URI describes resources identified by telephone numbers. This document obsoletes RFC 2806. [STANDARDS TRACK] </t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3966"/>
				<format type="TXT" octets="40783" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3966.txt"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC3629">
				<front>
					<title>UTF-8, a transformation format of ISO 10646</title>
					<author initials="F." surname="Yergeau" fullname="F. Yergeau">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date year="2003" month="November"/>
					<abstract>
						<t>ISO/IEC 10646-1 defines a large character set called the Universal Character Set (UCS) which encompasses most of the world's writing systems. The originally proposed encodings of the UCS, however, were not compatible with many current applications and protocols, and this has led to the development of UTF-8, the object of this memo. UTF-8 has the characteristic of preserving the full US-ASCII range, providing compatibility with file systems, parsers and other software that rely on US-ASCII values but are transparent to other values. This memo obsoletes and replaces RFC 2279. </t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="STD" value="63"/>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3629"/>
				<format type="TXT" octets="33856" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3629.txt"/>
			</reference>
		</references>
		<references title="Non-Normative References">
			<reference anchor="uri-clarification" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/uri-clarification/">
				<front>
					<title>URIs, URLs, and URNs: Clarifications and Recommendations 1.0</title>
					<author>
						<organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="September" year="2001"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="W3C" value="uri-clarification "/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC2368">
				<front>
					<title>The mailto URL scheme</title>
					<author initials="P. E." surname="Hoffmann" fullname="Paul E. Hoffmann">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="L." surname="Masinter" fullname="Larry Masinter">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="J." surname="Zawinski" fullname="Jamie Zawinski">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date month="June" year="1998"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2368"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC2838">
				<front>
					<title>Uniform Resource Identifiers for Television Broadcasts</title>
					<author initials="D." surname="Zigmond" fullname="D. Zigmond">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="M." surname="Vickers" fullname="M. Vickers">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date year="2000" month="May"/>
					<abstract>
						<t>This document describes a widely-implemented URI scheme, as World-Wide Web browsers are starting to appear on a variety of consumer electronic devices, such as television sets and television set-top boxes, which are capable of receiving television programming from either terrestrial broadcast, satellite broadcast, or cable. In this context there is a need to reference television broadcasts using the URI format described in RFC 2396. This memo provides information for the Internet community. </t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2838"/>
				<format type="TXT" octets="11405" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2838.txt"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC2629">
				<front>
					<title>Writing I-Ds and RFCs using XML</title>
					<author initials="M.T." surname="Rose" fullname="Marshall T. Rose">
						<organization>Invisible Worlds, Inc.</organization>
						<address>
							<postal>
								<street>660 York Street</street>
								<city>San Francisco</city>
								<region>CA</region>
								<code>94110</code>
								<country>US</country>
							</postal>
							<phone>+1 415 695 3975</phone>
							<email>mrose@not.invisible.net</email>
							<uri>http://invisible.net/</uri>
						</address>
					</author>
					<date year="1999" month="June"/>
					<area>General</area>
					<keyword>RFC</keyword>
					<keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>
					<keyword>I-D</keyword>
					<keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
					<keyword>XML</keyword>
					<keyword>Extensible Markup Language</keyword>
					<abstract>
						<t>This memo presents a technique for using XML (Extensible Markup Language) as a source format for documents in the Internet-Drafts (I-Ds) and Request for Comments (RFC) series.</t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2629"/>
				<format type="TXT" octets="48677" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2629.txt"/>
				<format type="HTML" octets="0" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2629.html"/>
				<format type="XML" octets="53464" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2629.xml"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="WAP">
				<front>
					<title>Wireless Application Protocol - Architecture Specification (WAP-210-WAPArch-20010712)</title>
					<author>
						<organization>WAP Forum</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="July" year="2001"/>
				</front>
			</reference>
		</references>
		<section title="Syntax of 'telephone-subscriber'" anchor="telephone-subscriber-syntax">
			<t>The following syntax is reproduced from Section 3 of RFC 3966 <xref target="RFC3966"/>. It defines the &lt;telephone-subscriber> part used in the SMS URI scheme syntax. Please note that it includes Erratum 203 for RFC 3966, which changes the definition of &lt;isdn-subaddress>.</t>
			<t>
				<figure>
					<artwork>
telephone-subscriber = global-number / local-number
global-number        = global-number-digits *par
local-number         = local-number-digits *par context *par
par                  = parameter / extension / isdn-subaddress
isdn-subaddress      = ";isub=" 1*paramchar
extension            = ";ext=" 1*phonedigit
context              = ";phone-context=" descriptor
descriptor           = domainname / global-number-digits
global-number-digits = "+" *phonedigit DIGIT *phonedigit
local-number-digits  =
   *phonedigit-hex (HEXDIG / "*" / "#")*phonedigit-hex
domainname           = *( domainlabel "." ) toplabel [ "." ]
domainlabel          = alphanum
                       / alphanum *( alphanum / "-" ) alphanum
toplabel             = ALPHA / ALPHA *( alphanum / "-" ) alphanum
parameter            = ";" pname ["=" pvalue ]
pname                = 1*( alphanum / "-" )
pvalue               = 1*paramchar
paramchar            = param-unreserved / unreserved / pct-encoded
unreserved           = alphanum / mark
mark                 = "-" / "_" / "." / "!" / "~" / "*" /
                       "'" / "(" / ")"
pct-encoded          = "%" HEXDIG HEXDIG
param-unreserved     = "[" / "]" / "/" / ":" / "&amp;" / "+" / "$"
phonedigit           = DIGIT / [ visual-separator ]
phonedigit-hex       = HEXDIG / "*" / "#" / [ visual-separator ]
visual-separator     = "-" / "." / "(" / ")"
alphanum             = ALPHA / DIGIT</artwork>
				</figure>
			</t>			
		</section>
	</back>
</rfc>
