<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-wilde-rfc6906bis-00">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="Profiles">Identifying Profiles on the Web</title>
        <author initials="E." surname="Wilde" fullname="Erik Wilde">
            <organization>CA Technologies</organization>
            <address>
                <email>erik.wilde@dret.net</email>
                <uri>http://dret.net/netdret/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date day="1" month="January" year="2018"/>
        <abstract>
            <t>Profiles are a way to refine an existing media type so that the original semantics are not affected, but to represent the fact that the media type now adheres to additional constraints (extensions and/or limitations of the media type). Any representation that conforms to a profile also conforms to the original media type. Profiles were introduced in RFC 6906, which defined a link relation type and suggested that media types should support a profile parameter. This specification obsoletes the original text with some clarifications, and also introduces a registered HTTP preference for profiles, which allows profiles to be negotiated without the need for a profile media type parameter.</t>
        </abstract>
        <note title="Note to Readers">
            <t>Please discuss this draft on the ART mailing list (<eref target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/art"/>).</t>
            <t>Online access to all versions and files is available on GitHub (<eref target="https://github.com/dret/I-D/tree/master/rfc6906bis"/>).</t>
        </note>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction" anchor="introduction">
            <t>Profiles were introduced by RFC 6906 <xref target="RFC6906"/> as a way to represent additional semantics for existing media types. The original specification defined a link relation type for indicating the presence of a profile, and also suggested for media types to consider supporting profile parameters.</t>
            <t>Experience has shown that both approaches are not ideal. A link relation type typically implies a traversable link, while a profile "link" is intended to be an identifier only. A media type parameter must be defined by a media type itself, and so far only very few media types support a parameter for representing profile information. As a way to improve this situation, this updated specification adds a new way to represent profile information at the HTTP level (Section <xref target="profile-http"/>).</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Terminology" anchor="terminology">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Profiles" anchor="profiles">
            <t>The concept of a profile has no strict definition on the Internet or on the web. For the purpose of this specification, a profile can be described as additional constraints that can be used to process a resource representation, such as structural constraints, conventions, extensions, or any other aspects that do not alter the basic media type semantics. A profile MUST NOT change the basic semantics of the resource representation (as defined by the media type) when processed without profile knowledge, so that clients both with and without knowledge of a profiled resource can safely use the same representation.</t>
            <t>An easy way to conceptualize profiles is to imagine both a media type and a profile having a schema (even though none of them need to have one). If the profile schema is a refinement/augmentation of the media type schema, and if any valid profile instance is a valid media type instance, then the profile indeed is one according to the working definition used in this specification.</t>
            <t>While this specification associates profiles with resource representations, creators and users of profiles MAY define and manage them in a way that allows them to be used across media types; thus, they could be associated with various representations of a resource (i.e., using the same profile URI for different media types). However, such a design is outside of the scope of this specification, and clients SHOULD treat profiles as always being associated with a resource representation (i.e., media types).</t>
            <t>Profiles can be combined, meaning that a single resource representation can conform to zero or any number of profiles. Depending on the profile support of clients, it is possible that the same resource representation, when linked to a number of profiles, can be processed with different sets of processing rules, based on the profile support of individual clients.</t>
            <t>Profiles are identified by URI. However, as is the case with, for example, XML namespace URIs, the URI in this case only serves as an identifier, meaning that the presence of a specific URI has to be sufficient for a client to assert that a resource representation conforms to a profile. Thus, clients SHOULD treat profile URIs as identifiers and not as links, but profiles MAY be defined in a way that the URIs do identify retrievable profile descriptions and thus can be accessed by clients by dereferencing the profile URI. For profiles intended for use in environments where clients may encounter unknown profile URIs, profile maintainers SHOULD consider to make the profile URI dereferencable and provide useful documentation at that URI. The design and representation of such profile descriptions, however, is outside the scope of this specification.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Profiles and HTTP" anchor="profile-http">
            <t>The original profile specification <xref target="RFC6906"/> suggested that media types should consider supporting a profile media type parameter. The idea was that this would make the profile visible on the HTTP level, and ideally even negotiable. However, this also meant that it was the media type's responsibility to support such a parameter, and since media types are typically widely used and long lived, only very few support such a media type parameter.</t>
            <t>The HTTP Prefer header <xref target="RFC7240"/> introduces a mechanism where clients and servers can communicate preferences, without binding those to the media type. Specifically, the header is based on a registry which allows new preferences to be registered, so that new preferences can be defined and then exchanged, based on that header. This means that preferences can be exchanged in a way which is independent from the media type. One way to use this mechanism, as described in Section <xref target="IANA-profile-http-preference"/>, is to define a preference that represents profile information.</t>
            <t>Using the HTTP Prefer header, profile information becomes readily accessible at the HTTP level, without the need for the media type to support or even know the notion of profiles.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Profile HTTP Preference" anchor="profile-http-preference">
            <t>...</t>
        </section>
        <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="IANA">
            <t>...</t>
            <section title="Link Relation Type" anchor="IANA-profile-link-relation-type">
                <t>This specification updates the "Link Relation Type" registry entry for "profile" in Web Linking <xref target="RFC8288"/> to refer to this document.</t>
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t>Relation Name: profile</t>
                        <t>Description: Identifying that a resource representation conforms to a certain profile, without affecting the non-profile semantics of the resource representation.</t>
                        <t>Reference: RFC XXXX</t>
                        <t>Notes: Profile URIs are primarily intended to be used as identifiers, and thus clients SHOULD NOT indiscriminately access profile URIs.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="HTTP Preference" anchor="IANA-profile-http-preference">
                <t>The HTTP Preference below has been registered by IANA per Section 5.1 of RFC 7240 <xref target="RFC7240"/>:</t>
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t>Preference: profile</t>
                        <t>Value:</t>
                        <t>Optional Parameters:</t>
                        <t>Description:</t>
                        <t>Reference: RFC XXXX</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            <reference  anchor='RFC2119' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119'>
                <front>
                    <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
                    <author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'><organization /></author>
                    <date year='1997' month='March' />
                    <abstract><t>In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification. These words are often capitalized. This document defines these words as they should be interpreted in IETF documents. This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14'/>
                <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119'/>
                <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2119'/>
            </reference>
            <reference  anchor='RFC6906' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6906'>
                <front>
                    <title>The 'profile' Link Relation Type</title>
                    <author initials='E.' surname='Wilde' fullname='E. Wilde'><organization /></author>
                    <date year='2013' month='March' />
                    <abstract><t>This specification defines the 'profile' link relation type that allows resource representations to indicate that they are following one or more profiles. A profile is defined not to alter the semantics of the resource representation itself, but to allow clients to learn about additional semantics (constraints, conventions, extensions) that are associated with the resource representation, in addition to those defined by the media type and possibly other mechanisms.</t></abstract>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6906'/>
                <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC6906'/>
            </reference>
            <reference  anchor='RFC7240' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7240'>
                <front>
                    <title>Prefer Header for HTTP</title>
                    <author initials='J.' surname='Snell' fullname='J. Snell'><organization /></author>
                    <date year='2014' month='June' />
                    <abstract><t>This specification defines an HTTP header field that can be used by a client to request that certain behaviors be employed by a server while processing a request.</t></abstract>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7240'/>
                <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC7240'/>
            </reference>
            <reference  anchor='RFC8288' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8288'>
                <front>
                    <title>Web Linking</title>
                    <author initials='M.' surname='Nottingham' fullname='M. Nottingham'><organization /></author>
                    <date year='2017' month='October' />
                    <abstract><t>This specification defines a model for the relationships between resources on the Web (&quot;links&quot;) and the type of those relationships (&quot;link relation types&quot;).</t><t>It also defines the serialisation of such links in HTTP headers with the Link header field.</t></abstract>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8288'/>
                <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC8288'/>
            </reference>
        </references>
<!--
      <references title="Informative References">
      </references>
 -->     
      <section title="Acknowledgements">
          <t>Thanks for comments and suggestions provided by Ruben Verborgh.</t>
          <t>Acknowledgements in the original specification <xref target="RFC6906"/> included Erlend Hamnaberg, Markus Lanthaler, Simon Mayer, Mark Nottingham, Julian Reschke, James Snell, Herbert Van de Sompel, and Tim Williams. These acknowledgements are equally relevant for this updated version of the specification.</t>
      </section>
    </back>
</rfc>
