<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" ipr="full2026" docName="draft-wilde-sms-service-00">
	<front>
		<title>Registration of GSTN SMS Service Qualifier</title>
		<author initials="E." surname="Wilde" fullname="Erik Wilde">
			<organization>Swiss Federal Institute of Technology</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>ETH-Zentrum</street>
					<city>8092 Zurich</city>
					<country>Switzerland</country>
				</postal>
				<phone>+41-1-6325132</phone>
				<email>ietf@dret.net</email>
				<uri>http://dret.net/netdret/</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date day="26" month="December" year="2001"/>
		<abstract>
			<t>This memo describes the registration of the Short Message Service (SMS) as a registered IANA service selector for Global Switched Telephone Network (GSTN) numbers. SMS is not available for all GSTN subscribers, but it has proven very popular with users of the Global System for Mobile Communications (GSM), and has also been adapted to other telephone network technologies such as the Integrated Services Digital Network (ISDN).</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction">
			<t>The capitalized key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
			<section title="What is GSM?">
				<t>GSM (Global System for Mobile Communications) is a digital mobile phone standard which is used extensively in many parts of the world. First named after its frequency band around 900 MHz, GSM-900 has provided the basis for several other networks utilizing GSM technology, in particular GSM networks operating in the frequency bands around 1800 MHz and 1900 MHz. When referring to "GSM" in this document, we mean any of these GSM-based networks that operate a short message service.</t>
			</section>
			<section title="What is SMS?">
				<t>The Short Message Service <xref target="SMS"/> is an integral part of the GSM network technology. It has been very successful and currently is a major source of revenue for most GSM operators. SMS as a service is so successful that other Global Switched Telephone Network (GSTN) technologies have adapted it as well, in particular the Integrated Services Digital Network (ISDN). Because of this development, this memo uses the term "SMS client" to refer to user agents who are able to send and/or receive SMS messages.</t>
				<section title="SMS content">
					<t>GSM SMS messages are alphanumeric paging messages that can be sent to and SMS clients. SMS messages have a maximum length of 160 characters (7-bit characters from the GSM character set <xref target="SMS-CHAR"/>), or 140 octets. Other character sets (such as UCS-2 16-bit characters, resulting in 80 character messages) MAY also be supported <xref target="SMS-CHAR"/>, but are defined as being OPTIONAL by the SMS specification.</t>
					<t>While the 160 character variety for SMS messages is by far the most widely used one, there are numerous other content types for SMS messages, such as small bitmaps ("operator logos") and simple formats for musical notes ("ring tones"). However, these formats are proprietary and are not considered in this memo.</t>
					<t>SMS messages are very limited in length (140 octets), so several methods exist to concatenate SMS messages. However, none of these methods is standardized, and different manufacturers of mobile phones implement different methods of message concatenation. Therefore, SMS message concatenation is not taken into consideration by this memo. SMS clients composing messages may still employ concatenation methods, but they MUST be aware that they do so at their own risk, possibly using a method that is not supported by the receiving SMS client.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="SMS infrastructure">
					<t>SMS messages can be transmitted over an SMS client's network interface using the signalling channels of the underlying GSTN infrastructure, so there is no delay for call setup. Alternatively, SMS messages MAY be submitted through other front-ends (for example such as Web services), which makes it possible for SMS clients to run on computers which are not directly connected to a GSTN network supporting SMS.</t>
					<t>SMS messages are stored by an entity called Short Message Service Centre (SMSC), and sent to the recipient when the subscriber connects to the network. The number of a cooperative SMSC must be known to the SMS sender (ie, the entity submitting the SMS message to a GSTN infrastructure) when sending the message (usually, the SMSC's number is configured in the SMS client and specific for the network operator to which the sender has subscribed). In most situations, the SMSC number is part of the sending SMS client's configuration. However, in some special cases (such as when the SMS recipient only accepts messages from a certain SMSC), it may be necessary to send the SMS message over a specific SMSC.</t>
					<t>Short messages can be mobile terminated (MT) or mobile originated (MO). MT messages are the ones that arrive at SMS clients; MO messages are sent by SMS clients. Networks may support either, both, or none of these. For the purpose of this memo, it is important that the sending SMS client is allowed to submit MO messages, and that the receiver is allowed to receive MT messages.</t>
					<t>The exact setup of message submission and delivery is not subject of this memo, it may incorporate additional hops in addition to the pure SMS transport. For example, the sending SMS client may use a Web service to submit the SMS message, and the receiving SMS client may be set up to forward the SMS to an email account. For the purpose of this memo, it is important that the receiver can be addressed by a GSTN number, and that the sender can submit an SMS message using this number.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="IANA registrations">
			<t>Based on the requirements defined in RFC 3191 <xref target="RFC3191"/>, the IANA registration forms for the "SMS" service-selector and "SMSC" qualif-type1 elements are defined here. Syntax definitions are given using the Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications <xref target="RFC2234"/>.</t>
			<section title='IANA registration form for GSTN address service-selector "SMS"'>
				<t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
To:      IANA@iana.org
Subject: Registration of new values for the GSTN address
         service-selector specifier "SMS"
</artwork>
					</figure>
				</t>
				<t>
					<list style="hanging">
						<t hangText="service-selector name:">SMS</t>
						<t hangText="Description of Use:">SMS - specify that the GSTN address refers to a GSTN subscriber who is capable of receiving messages using the GSM Short Message Service (SMS).</t>
						<t>For a complete description refer to RFC 3191 and draft-wilde-sms-service-00.</t>
						<t hangText="Security Considerations:">See the Security Consideration section of draft-wilde-sms-service-00.</t>
						<t hangText="Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:">
							<figure>
								<artwork>
Erik Wilde
Swiss Federal Institute of Technology
ETH-Zentrum
8092 Zurich
Switzerland
tel:+41-1-6325132
fax:+41-1-6321035
mailto:ietf@dret.net
						   	</artwork>
							</figure>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title='IANA registration form for GSTN address qualit-type1 keyword "SMSC" and value'>
				<t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
To:      IANA@iana.org
Subject: Registration of new values for the GSTN address
         qualif-type1 element "SMSC"
</artwork>
					</figure>
				</t>
				<t>
					<list style="hanging">
						<t hangText='qualif-type1 "keyword" name:'>SMSC</t>
						<t hangText='qualif-type1 "value" ABNF definition:'>The ABNF definition for the value of the SMSC keyword is taken from draft-allocchio-gstn-01</t>
						<t>
							<figure>
								<artwork>
sub-addr      =  gstn-phone
gstn-phone    =  ( global-phone / local-phone )
global-phone  =  "+" 1*( DIGIT / written-sep )
local-phone   =  [ exit-code ] dial-number / exit-code [ dial-number ]
exit-code     =  phone-string
dial-number   =  phone-string
phone-string  =  1*( DTMF / pause / tonewait / written-sep )
DTMF          =  ( DIGIT / "#" / "*" / "A" / "B" / "C" / "D" )
pause         =  "p"
tonewait      =  "w"
written-sep   =  ( "-" / "." )
							</artwork>
							</figure>
						</t>
						<t hangText="Description of Use:">SMSC - In some situations, it may be necessary to guide the sender of an SMS message to send the message via a certain Short Message Service Center (SMSC). If the SMSC qualif-type1 element is present, an SMS client SHOULD try to send the message first using the specified SMSC. If that fails, the SMS client MAY try another SMSC (such as the default SMSC for that client).</t>
						<t>Further description is available in draft-wilde-sms-service-00</t>
						<t hangText="Use Restriction:">The use of the "SMSC" qualif-type1 element is restricted to the "SMS" service-selector, it has no meaning outside the SMS service defined by the "SMS" service-selector.</t>
						<t hangText="Security Considerations:">See the Security Consideration section of draft-wilde-sms-service-00.</t>
						<t hangText="Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:">
							<figure>
								<artwork>
Erik Wilde
Swiss Federal Institute of Technology
ETH-Zentrum
8092 Zurich
Switzerland
tel:+41-1-6325132
fax:+41-1-6321035
mailto:ietf@dret.net
							   </artwork>
							</figure>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="Security Considerations">
			<t>SMS messages are transported without any provisions for privacy or integrity, so SMS users should be aware of these inherent security problems of SMS messages. Unlike electronic mail, where additional mechanisms exist to layer security features on top of the infrastructure, there is no such framework for SMS messages.</t>
			<t>SMS messages very often are delivered almost instantaneously (if the receiving SMS client is on line), but there is no guarantee for when SMS messages will be delivered. In particular, SMS messages between different network operators sometimes take a long time to be delivered (hours or even days) or are not delivered at all, so applications SHOULD NOT make any assumptions about the reliability and performance of SMS message transmission.</t>
			<t>In most networks, sending SMS messages is not a free service. Therefore, SMS clients MUST make sure that any action that incurs costs is acknowledged by the end user, unless explicitly instructed otherwise by the end user. If an SMS client has different ways of submitting an SMS message (such as a Web service and a phone line), then the end user MUST have a way to control which way is chosen.</t>
			<t>SMS clients often are limited devices (typically mobile phones), and the sending SMS client SHOULD NOT make any assumptions about the receiving SMS client supporting any non-standard services, such as message concatenation or proprietary content types. However, if the sending SMS client has prior knowledge about the receiving SMS client, then he MAY use this knowledge to compose non-standard SMS messages.</t>
		</section>
	</middle>
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			<reference anchor="SMS" target="http://pda.etsi.org/pda/home.asp?wki_id=6822">
				<front>
					<title>Digital Cellular Telecommunications System (Phase 2+); Technical realization of the Short Message Service (SMS); Point-to-Point (PP)</title>
					<author>
						<organization abbrev="ETSI">European Telecommunications Standards Institute</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="December" year="1998"/>
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="SMS-CHAR" target="http://pda.etsi.org/pda/home.asp?wki_id=4690">
				<front>
					<title>Digital Cellular Telecommunications System (Phase 2+) (GSM); Alphabets and language-specific information (GSM 03.38)</title>
					<author>
						<organization abbrev="ETSI">European Telecommunications Standards Institute</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="July" year="1996"/>
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC3191">
				<front>
					<title>Minimal GSTN address format in Internet Mail</title>
					<author initials="C." surname="Allocchio" fullname="C. Allocchio">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date month="October" year="2001"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3191"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC2234">
				<front>
					<title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
					<author initials="D. H." surname="Crocker" fullname="David H. Crocker">
						<organization>Internet Mail Consortium</organization>
						<address>
							<postal>
								<street>675 Spruce Dr.</street>
								<city>Sunnyvale</city>
								<region>CA</region>
								<code>94086</code>
								<country>US</country>
							</postal>
							<phone>+1 408 246 8253</phone>
							<facsimile>+1 408 249 6205</facsimile>
							<email>dcrocker@imc.org</email>
						</address>
					</author>
					<author initials="P." surname="Overell" fullname="Paul Overell">
						<organization>Demon Internet Ltd</organization>
						<address>
							<postal>
								<street>Dorking Business Park</street>
								<street>Dorking</street>
								<city>Surrey</city>
								<region>England</region>
								<code>RH4 1HN</code>
								<country>UK</country>
							</postal>
							<phone/>
							<email>paulo@turnpike.com</email>
						</address>
					</author>
					<date month="November" year="1997"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2234"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="draft-allocchio-gstn">
				<front>
					<title>Text string notation for Dial Sequences and GSTN / E.164 addresses</title>
					<author initials="C." surname="Allocchio" fullname="Claudio Allocchio">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date month="November" year="2001"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-allocchio-gstn-01"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="draft-wilde-sms-service-00">
				<front>
					<title>Registration of GSTN SMS Service Qualifier</title>
					<author initials="E." surname="Wilde" fullname="Erik Wilde">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date month="December" year="2001"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-wilde-sms-service-00"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC2119">
				<front>
					<title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
					<author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
						<organization>Harvard University</organization>
						<address>
							<postal>
								<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
								<street>Cambridge</street>
								<street>MA 02138</street>
							</postal>
							<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
						</address>
					</author>
					<date month="March" year="1997"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
			</reference>
		</references>
		<references title="Non-Normative References">
			<reference anchor="RFC2629">
				<front>
					<title>Writing I-Ds and RFCs using XML</title>
					<author initials="M.T." surname="Rose" fullname="Marshall T. Rose">
						<organization>Invisible Worlds, Inc.</organization>
						<address>
							<postal>
								<street>660 York Street</street>
								<city>San Francisco</city>
								<region>CA</region>
								<code>94110</code>
								<country>US</country>
							</postal>
							<phone>+1 415 695 3975</phone>
							<email>mrose@not.invisible.net</email>
							<uri>http://invisible.net/</uri>
						</address>
					</author>
					<date month="June" year="1999"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2629"/>
			</reference>
		</references>
		<section title="Where to send Comments">
			<t>Please send all comments about this document to Erik Wilde.</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Acknowledgements">
			<t>This document has been written using the IETF document DTD described in RFC 2629 <xref target="RFC2629"/>.</t>
		</section>
	</back>
</rfc>
